<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Covenant-renouncers, desperate-apostates opened in two letters, written by a Christian friend, to Mr. William Gurnal of Lavenham in the county of Suffolk : which may indefinitely serve as an admonition to all such Presbyterian ministers, or others, who have forced their consciences, not only to leap over, but to renounce their Solemn Covenant-obligation, to endeavor a reformation according to God's Word, and the extirpation of all prelatical superstition, and contrary thereunto, conform to those superstitious vanities, agianst which they had so solemnly sworn ... : together with an appendix concerning the Church of England in general.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34783</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18958300</idno>
  <idno type="VID">108481</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240861395</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40348</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18958300</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1666:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Covenant-renouncers, desperate-apostates opened in two letters, written by a Christian friend, to Mr. William Gurnal of Lavenham in the county of Suffolk : which may indefinitely serve as an admonition to all such Presbyterian ministers, or others, who have forced their consciences, not only to leap over, but to renounce their Solemn Covenant-obligation, to endeavor a reformation according to God's Word, and the extirpation of all prelatical superstition, and contrary thereunto, conform to those superstitious vanities, agianst which they had so solemnly sworn ... : together with an appendix concerning the Church of England in general.</title>
                  <author>Gurnall, William, 1617-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in Anti-turn-coat-street, and sold at the sign of Truths-delight ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 35.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Covenant theology.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Presbyterian Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108481:1"/>
            <p>COVENANT-RENOUNCERS, DESPERATE-APOSTATES. Opened in Two LETTERS, written by a <hi>Christian</hi> Friend, to Mr. <hi>WILLIAM GURNAL</hi> of <hi>Lavenham</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which may indefinitely serve as an Admonition to all such <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Ministers, or others, who have forced their Consciences, not only to leap over, but to <hi>Renounce</hi> their Solemn <hi>Covenant</hi>-Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>to endeavour a Reformation according to God's Word, and the Extirpation of all Prelatical Superstition;</hi> and contrary thereunto, conform to those Superstitious Vanities, against which they had so Solemnly SWORN.</p>
            <p>As also, to caution all that fear God, to take heed and beware of such men, and not adventure to attend upon their Preaching, lest they provoke God to jealousie, and pull down the Wrath of <hi>Jehovah</hi> upon themselves.</p>
            <p>Together with an <hi>APPENDIX</hi> concerning the <hi>Church of England</hi> in general.</p>
            <q>
               <p>But all the Princes said unto all the Congregation, We have SWORN unto them by the Lord God of Israel: Now therefore we may not touch them, — LEST WRATH BE ƲPON ƲS, BECAƲSE OF THE OATH which we sware unto them. <bibl>
                     <hi>Josh. 9.19, 20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>—Shall he prosper? shall he escape that doth such things? SHAL HE BREAK THE COVENANT, and be delivered? As I live, saith the Lord God, Surely in the place where the King dwelleth that made him King, whose OATH HE DESPISED, and whose COVENANT HE BRAKE, even with him in the midst of Babylon shall he die. <bibl>
                     <hi>Ezek. 17.15, 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Behold, ye trust in lying words, that cannot profit. Will ye steal, Murder, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery, and SWEAR FALSLY, and burn Incense unto Baal, — And come and stand before Me in this House which is called by my Name, and say, We are delivered to do all these abominations? <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 7.8, 9, 10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Dreadful is the Indignation of God, revealed against <hi>Covenant-breakers:</hi> But what his Wrath shall be against COVENANT-RENOUNCERS, Who can say?</p>
               <p>O my soul, come not thou into their secret: Ʋnto their Assembly, mine honour be be not thou united. <bibl>
                     <hi>Gen. 49.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in <hi>Anti-turn-coat</hi>-street, and sold at the sign of <hi>Truths-delight,</hi> right opposit to <hi>Back-sliding-alley.</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:108481:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:108481:2"/>
            <head>To all those that love God, and Jesus Christ in Sincerity and Truth, partakers of like precious Faith with the rest of his Saints and faithful followers, living in or near unto the Parish of <hi>Lavenham</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, to whom these Papers shall come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Christian Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know not whether you have taken up the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation before me, or not, but it is worthy of your <hi>serious</hi> consideration, <hi>That an Enemy under the vizor of a Friend, is far more danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, then an open and professed Adversary. David</hi> in his dayes took signal notice of this evil-Spirit, manifesting it self in wicked and ungodly men; for, speaking of the wicked man, he expresseth himself thus; <hi>He hath put forth his hands against such as be at peace with him: he hath BROKEN HIS COVENANT. The words of his mouth were smoother than butter, but war was in his heart: his words were softer than oyl, yet were they drawn swords;</hi> Psal. 55.20, 21. Now that hatred which coucheth it self under the <hi>smoothest</hi> words, and <hi>softest</hi> expressions, is most sharp, and deeply piercing: and that enmity which cloatheth it self with pretended friendship, is most cruel and diabolical. <hi>Art thou in health, my Brother?</hi> was <hi>Joab</hi>'s salutation to <hi>Amasa, and took him by the beard to kiss him;</hi> when immediately <hi>he smote him with the sword in the fifth rib, and shed out his bowels to the ground,</hi> 2 Sam. 20.9, 10. <hi>Judas</hi> also when he betrayed our Lord Jesus, saluted him with, <hi>Hail Master, and kissed him,</hi> Mat. 26.49. And it is beyond all doubt that Jesus <hi>Christ</hi> hath no greater enemies in the world at this day, than many, who pretend very highly for his interest, and glory;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108481:3"/>and would be accounted the only promoters of his Worship and Service amongst men: The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that <hi>generation of Vipers,</hi> pretended high for Religion and Godliness, and were found very busie in <hi>building the Tombs of the Prophets, and garnishing the Sepulchres of the Righteous,</hi> professing, that if they <hi>had been in the dayes of their fathers, they would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the Prophets</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Matth. 23.29, 30</note>; and yet never theless by their works they witnessed against themselves, that they <hi>allowed the deeds of their fathers</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 11 48.</note>, in killing the Prophets; and by their cruel persecutions of the Saints, brought upon their own heads <hi>all the righteous blood shed upon the earth, from the blood of righteous Abel, unto the blood of Zacharias, the son of Barachias, slain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Temple and the Altar</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Matth, 23.33, 35</note>. Suitable hereunto is that also of the Prophet <hi>Isaiah, Your Brethren that hated you, that cast you out for my Name-sake, said, Let the Lord be glorified; Isa.</hi> 66.5. And the Great <hi>Anti-Christ,</hi> or <hi>MAN of SIN,</hi> (as the Apostle stiles him) <hi>sitteth in the Temple of God</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Thes. 2.4.</note>; as though he were the first-born of his sons and servants, soley devoted to the promotion of his Worship amongst the children of men: when nevertheless he is <hi>Christs</hi> most dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enemy, <hi>whom the Lord shall consume with the Spirit of his mouth, and destroy with the brightness of his coming;</hi> 2 Thess. 2.8. From these premises I shall commend unto you <hi>(Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Friends)</hi> the following Inferences and Deductions;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let it seem no strange thing unto you, that a person of such seeming piety and zeal for God and Godliness, as he to whom these Papers relate, hath been esteemed, (with divers others) should notwithstanding put forth his hand to the service of the <hi>Beast,</hi> and the <hi>false Prophet:</hi> for the truth is, <hi>Mystery Babylon, the Mother of Harlots, and Abominations of the Earth</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Revel. 17.5.</note>, could never have ascended so high upon her throne of dignity and honour in the world, had she not had some from time to time amongst her sons, very eminent, both for parts and abilities: and likewise for seeming Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Zeal for God: When once Satan can prevail with such men as these, to engage in his work, he may say of them, (as <hi>David</hi> of the Sword of <hi>Goliah) There are none like to these,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:108481:3"/>for the promoting of his Kingdom of darkness in the world; especially if they retain any competent esteem in the minds of men, and pass in common repute for <hi>good Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let the premises also (my <hi>dear Brethren</hi>) teach you this word of <hi>Christian care</hi> and <hi>caution, viz.</hi> to beware of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with men of this character; for he that cometh against you with a <hi>kiss,</hi> and a salute, <hi>Art thou in health, my Brother?</hi> may sooner <hi>shed your bowels on the ground,</hi> than he that appeareth in open hostility with Sword and Spear: And as the sharpest hook hath oft-times the pleasantest bait, so the Devil and his Agents do frequently make use of some excellent Truths and glosses, to prevail with men to swallow the most destructive Errors and Superstitions: <hi>Thus it is written,</hi> saith the Devil to Christ, when notwithstanding he tempted him to the greatest disloyalty to God his Father imaginable. <hi>A little leaven</hi> (saith the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6.) <hi>leaveneth the whole lump.</hi> Therefore let all such as desire to <hi>worship</hi> God <hi>in Spirit and in Truth;</hi> and who tremble to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him, by joyning with Superstition and Profaneness in his Worship and Service, avoid all communion with such men as these, in their way of Worship, as they would escape a dangerous snare of death.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Foenum habet in cornu: longe fugiam.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A lock of hay ty'd to their horn, they have:</l>
               <l>Far from them let us flee, our selves to save.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="3">3. Yet once more, Let all the Children of God be from hence informed, how great service those do for God, and the Christian World, by whose means the wickedness of such men as these, shall be detected and laid open. For, 1. This is an happy means to put a stop to their further progress in this evil way; and consequently to prevent much danger that might otherwise ensue to the precious souls of many, who possibly might be infected with, and ensnared by their evil practices:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9.</note>
               <hi>They shall proceed no further</hi> (saith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle) <hi>for their folly shall be made manifest unto all men.</hi> The detection and discovery of the madness and folly of an evil course or undertaking, is an excellent preservative unto
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108481:4"/>others from suffering themselves to be entangled therein. <hi>Surely in vain is the net spread in the sight of any bird,</hi> saith the Wise-man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.17. And 2dly. It is an opportunity of great advantage put into the hands of these evil-minded men themselves also, which through the blessing of God, may happily tend to their repentance and restoration: for, that which more private addresses will not do, God is sometimes pleased to effect by more publick shame: And certainly if ever any man stood in need of this Antidote, against the Poison of his own deceitful heart, <hi>viz.</hi> to be brought to reflect upon himself with shame, and to cover his face with sackcloth and ashes, surely Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> is the man: who if we compare himself with himself, may not his Motto be,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui me in me quaerit, non me, ut me, invenerit in me.</hi> i. e.</l>
                  <l>To find me, in me, who-e'r shall me seek,</l>
                  <l>Will in me, to me, never find me like.</l>
               </q> One while he appears as if <hi>wrapt up into the third Heavens,</hi> with zeal for God: another while as if drawn like <hi>a Star from Heaven</hi> by the <hi>tail of the Dragon.</hi> One while up goes the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and down with <hi>Episcopacy</hi> and Superstitious Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; another while down with the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and up with <hi>Prelacy</hi> and <hi>Common-prayer-book-devotion.</hi> One while <hi>all for Christ,</hi> and a <hi>Reformation according to God's Word:</hi> another while <hi>a little</hi> (at least) <hi>for Antichrist</hi> and the <hi>rebuilding of the Synagogue of Satan.</hi> One while he appears as one of the <hi>houshold of Faith,</hi> sitting and putting on the <hi>Christian Armour;</hi> another while as if he were of the house and linage of that Soldier in <hi>Plautus,</hi> who represents his prudence in war thus:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quà illi pugnabant maximè, ego fugiebam maxime.</hi> i. e.</l>
                  <l>Where men were fiercest in the fight,</l>
                  <l>I made away by swiftest flight.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> alone in these horrible defilements, hateful to the Soul of God &amp; his Saints; but he is compassed about with a <hi>Cloud of Witnesses,</hi> (even in the County where himself liveth, as well as elsewhere) men of the same order of <hi>Antichristian Priesthood,</hi> and Brethren in the said iniquity with himself; Witness Mr. <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Cavendish,</hi> who upon one Lord's-day preached his <hi>Farewel-Sermon,</hi> and argued very
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108481:4"/>strongly, and with many considerations, the unlawfulness of <hi>Common-prayer-book-conformity;</hi> and so took his <hi>Farewel</hi> of the Congregation: But by the very next Lord's-day following, he had (it seems) met with some <hi>Episcopal eye-salve,</hi> which wrought so effectually with him, that it immediately closed his <hi>right-eye,</hi> by which the Lord's-day before, he saw such great deformity in Common-prayer-book-devotion: and also opened his <hi>left-eye</hi> to see <hi>Conformity-truth</hi> in that asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which the Apostle gives notice to be only <hi>supposed</hi> by some in his dayes, viz. <hi>that Gain is Godliness,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.5. and then with much zeal and heat preached up <hi>Subjection to higher Powers:</hi> not considering that there are Powers higher than those on earth, which whether it be right to obey rather, or before men, or not; judge ye.</p>
            <p>To these may also be added for company Mr. <hi>Hudson</hi> of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Knights</hi> of <hi>Ipswich,</hi> Dr. <hi>Harison</hi> of <hi>Hadly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Blac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerby</hi> of <hi>Stowe,</hi> with more than a <hi>good many</hi> besides, who have all bowed themselves to the <hi>Whore of Babylon;</hi> and given hostages to the <hi>Prince of the power of the Air,</hi> that they will never make any great inroad into his Kingdom in the world; or do any great execution upon the powers of sin and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness amongst men. These all, (with many others of their fellows and companions in these <hi>broad wayes</hi>) have given the world a lively testimony, that <hi>the Dragon, that old Serpent, which is the Devil and Satan,</hi> is not yet <hi>bound, and cast into the bottomless pit, and shut up from deceiving the Nations any more</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3.</note>: But contrarywise, that he hath been at work in the world, and <hi>with his tail hath drawn some of the Stars from Heaven, and cast them to the Earth.</hi> A small pittance of the glory and honour, with the profits and pleasures of this world, in conjunction (possibly) with the fear of suffering for <hi>Christs sake,</hi> hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed many of the same <hi>Tribe</hi> and <hi>Coat</hi> with these, to quit their station in <hi>Christ's Vineyard,</hi> and give the right-hand of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship to his deadly enemy, <hi>Antichrist;</hi> yea, and to <hi>renounce</hi> their <hi>Covenanted Reformation,</hi> &amp;c. So that it may be too truly said of Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> in respect of these abominations,
<q>
                  <l>— <hi>Flagrat vitio gentisque, suoque.</hi> i.e.</l>
                  <l>He burneth with a vice, that is</l>
                  <l>His fellows vice, as well as his,</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:108481:5"/>Who encourage and strengthen the hands one of another, much like as the <hi>Carpenter</hi> and the <hi>Goldsmith</hi> did, of whom the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> speaketh
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 41.7.</note> justifying each one his Brother, as <hi>Jerusalem justified her sisters, Sodom</hi> and <hi>Samaria</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.51, 52</note>. Though amongst this <hi>Synagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and corrupted Tribe of Priests, Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> (possibly) may have merited the shame and ignominy to be reputed one of the <hi>first-born sons of folly,</hi> in ascending up to the top of so high a mountain of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to, and contestation with, that generation of men, and way of worship; into the polluted gulf whereof he hath now descended; and in the judgment of the Apostle <hi>Paul, made himself a transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor, in building again the things which he destroyed</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.18</note>; or rather labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vain so to do: either not believing, or else not duly consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they that <hi>partake with Babylon in her sins, shall also receive of her plagues</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4.</note>: which whether it be believed or not, shall certainly be fulfilled, and <hi>her plagues shall come in one day, death, and mourning, and famine, and she shall be utterly burnt with fire: for strong is the Lord God, who judgeth her</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 8.</note>. Then shall every one that hath made himself a <hi>bondslave</hi> to her, <hi>call unto the Mountains and Rocks, to fall on them, and hide them from the face of him that sitteth on the Throne, and from the Wrath of the Lamb. For the great Day of his Wrath</hi> shall <hi>come, and who shall be able to stand?</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16, 17.</note> Therefore be astonished, O <hi>Gurnal,</hi> with thy fellows, and tremble all ye that have been perfidious in the Covenant of your God: <hi>For he will enter into the house of him that sweareth falsly by his Name</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zec.</hi> 4.5</note>, and <hi>will be a swift Witness against the False-Swearer</hi>
               <note place="margin">†. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5.</note>; yea, <hi>the sinners in Sion shall be afraid, fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness shall surprize the Hypocrite</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 33.14.</note>.</p>
            <p>But (to draw to a conclusion) I have but one thing more to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint my <hi>Christian Friends</hi> with, before they and I part, for the present; and that is, That these Letters were sent to Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> many months ago, ever since which time, until now, I have waited in expectation that some good effect would have been wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by them; but finding by due observation that he still remains under the guilt, and in the practice of his sinful conformity, to the dishonour of God, and the great scandal of Religion; I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore exposed the written Copy to your view, (the former of the two is <hi>verbatim</hi> as it was sent: the latter, is the substance of what was sent him, a little abreviated) Let me (for a close) caution all those unto whose view this Manuscript may happen to come, to be warned by other mens falls, to look well to your standing
<note n="†" place="bottom">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12.</note>; <hi>lest you also be led away with the errour of the wicked,</hi> and <hi>fall from your own stedfastness</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17.</note>. The Lord grant that these Papers may be a means to preserve you from all pollution and defilement in the Superstitions of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that her plagues may not be your por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4.</note>.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:108481:5"/>
            <head>A LETTER sent to Mr. <hi>William Gurnal,</hi> the <hi>5th</hi> of August, <hi>1663.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHether it was my happiness, or unhappiness, to hear of, and be in some degree (though remotely) acquainted with your gifts and parts in preaching; your (sometimes) seeming zeal for God, piety, and holiness of life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I cannot well determine: for though all manner of knowledge, either of persons or things, be in some kind or other beneficial, it being an undoubted maxime, that, <hi>Verum &amp; Bonum convertuntur:</hi> yet some know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge may be accompanied with such circumstances that may render it more burdensom and offensive, than commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious or advantagious. You have of late made such a disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of your self, &amp; unvailed (your <hi>face,</hi> shal I say? or rather) your <hi>heart,</hi> that the meanest round about you have gained thus much, to say, <hi>Now they know you:</hi> But (alas) this <hi>gain</hi> hath occasioned such a considerable <hi>loss</hi> in the things of the peace and joy of your real <hi>Christian Friends,</hi> that they have cause in abundance to wish for their former ignorance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning you, and that you had given them no such <hi>new</hi> Character of your self, as now you have done. Indeed it cannot but deduct much from the comfort of your cordial Friends, to see you, who in former days had obtained a large proportion of that <hi>Name,</hi> which the Wiseman saith, <hi>is better than precious Oyntment</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.1.</note>: yea, who were esteemed as a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster in Israel;</hi> an Armed Souldier of <hi>Jesus Christ;</hi> and an <hi>eminent Labourer in Gospel-things;</hi> who for your work-sake, were had in <hi>double honour;</hi> I say, to see you, now the Sun of your life seems past its <hi>Meridian,</hi> and the evening of your dayes to approach; when (for any thing you know to the contrary) your <hi>Race</hi> was almost run; your <hi>Victory</hi> well nigh obtained, and your <hi>Crown</hi> near ready to put on; then to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108481:6"/>sake your Colours, face about, and change your course; to <hi>lose the things that you had wrought,</hi> turn <hi>Renegado</hi> from those Truths of <hi>Christ</hi> which you had professed at so high a rate of zeal and fervency, and to pull down and destroy, as with both hands, what formerly you had been labouring so many years to build up and plant: in short, to see the favour of your <hi>precious Name</hi> here, turned into a <hi>noisom &amp; stinking Dunghil</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7.</note>: and your eternal Crown hereafter hazarded, if not forfeited and lost
<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>ult. Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10.26. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.10, 11.</note>: how can it but grieve the hearts and sad the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of such as sincerely love either you or Jesus Christ? And sorry we are that Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> should dash his foot against that stone at which the <hi>prophane Formalists</hi> of this world, stumble and fall from day to day: What! could you not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure one encounter for Christ? Could you not stand against one on-set? Where was your <hi>Spiritual Armour</hi> become? Had you parted with it all to others, and kept none of it for your own use, when you stood in most need? Had you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got your Lord and Master, who when the great Enemy temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him (not only with a small pittance of this worlds glory, which was the highest of your temptation, but) even with <hi>all the Kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Matth</hi> 4.8, 9.</note>: yet could not prevail with him to <hi>conform</hi> in the least? And what can you plead by way of excuse for your <hi>Conformity,</hi> but might have bin argued in our Saviors case with ten degrees of plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible probability more than can be in yours? Can you plead the <hi>lawfulness</hi> of your conformity in it self? [Surely all such pleadings will make you ashamed, being in direct opposition to the Truth; as now begins to be evidently visible and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest to all consciencious and seeing Christians:] But in our Saviours case, what hindred but Christ might <hi>lawfully</hi> make <hi>bread</hi> of <hi>stones</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Matth</hi> 4.3.</note>, since at another time he made <hi>wine</hi> of <hi>water</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.9.</note>? —Can you say, You conform, not to get honour or great estates in the world, but only for a competent maintenance for your self and family, which must not starve; for you are bound to take care of, and provide for them? [Is not this sinfully to distrust the providence of God, as if he had not provided honest and lawful means for the maintenance of his People?] yet however, in our Saviours case, it was only for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108481:6"/>
               <hi>bread,</hi> not superfluity of dainties; and that too, not to please his appetite only, but to satisfie hunger
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.2.</note>. —Can you yet again argue, They are things <hi>indifferent</hi> that you submit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? [This will certainly put all the wit, and parts, and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you have (with all the Colledge of <hi>Episcopal</hi> Doctors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides) upon the Rack to justifie and make good, and yet will it be too hard for you all at last.] But in our Saviours case, it was only <hi>stones</hi> that he was solicited to take and make bread of: and what more <hi>indifferent</hi> thing could he have taken than a few stones? No man would claim a propriety in them; who could have charged him with wronging them in such a case? Once more, Can you plead you break no <hi>positive</hi> Law? [Your proof for that is to seek, and will never be found so long as <hi>Lordly Episcopacy</hi> lives in the world.] But in our Saviours case, What <hi>positive</hi> Precept had he broke?—But come on a little further; Will the <hi>goodness of your end</hi> ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie your Conformity? Is it your zeal to the Gospel, and the preaching thereof? [This Argument is light as vanity it self: for, as <hi>the wrath of man worketh not the Righteousness of God</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.20.</note>: So the Gospel of <hi>Christ</hi> is no wayes promoted by mans sin; We must not do evil that good may come of it; nor <hi>sin</hi> to make <hi>grace abound</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1, 2.</note>] But in our Saviours case, the end proposed was as good as yours can be, <hi>viz.</hi> the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation of himself to be the son of God. <hi>If thou be the Son of God, command that these stones be made bread</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Matth</hi> 4.3.</note>. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all these plausible pretences, being imposed upon him by the Devil, he disdains all <hi>conformity.</hi> But this grand Adversary sends a smaller force against you, only some of his Emissaries and Agents to assault you, with a less prevailing motive, to a more notorious act (at least less capable of a plausible plea) imposing on you things manifestly unlawful; derogatory unto Christ; destructive to the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; scandalous to the World; offensive to the Saints; uncharitable to your Imposers; and prejudicial to your own Soul: And you cowardly, not like a man, much less like a good <hi>Souldier</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> retreat, even before the fight began; the very threatnings of your enemy wrought the conquest over you, causing you to quit the Banner of Christ,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108481:7"/>and like (if not worse than) <hi>Issachar's Ass,</hi> bow downan prostrate your self unto the impositions of his adversary.</p>
            <p>But Sir, methinks I am in an extasie of admiration at the thoughts of your <hi>Conformity</hi> above many others, when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider your former Zeal and Eminency: What, Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> conform! concerning whom men were almost ready to say, (as sometimes <hi>Peter</hi> said of himself) <hi>though all men forsake</hi> Christ, renounce the Covenant, and submit to Episcopal conformity, yet Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> will not. How did you, when time was, preach up, <hi>Curse ye Meroz, &amp;c?</hi> How many Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers did you (by Arguments and Exhortations) thrust forth into the Warrs? How did you voluntarily, and zealously both take the Covenant, and importunely urge and press it upon others? Doth it become the same persons one day to sing <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> and cry <hi>Hosanna to the Son of David</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">Matth. 21.9.</note>; and another day to cry, <hi>Crucifie him, crucifie him</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 27.22, 23</note>? Give me leave to query with you, as sometimes the Apostle did with the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians,</hi> (with a little variation of words) <hi>Oh foolish</hi> Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>who hath bewitched you, that you should not</hi> continue in <hi>the Truth,</hi> before the eyes of whose mind <hi>Jesus Christ hath been evidently set forth? Are you so foolish? having begun in the Spirit, are you now made perfect by the flesh? Have you</hi> preached <hi>so many things in vain</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3.</note>? Are you now resolved to pull down with all your might what you have (by your preaching and writing) been labouring to build up all your dayes? Or, do you not take a direct course hereunto? For he that shall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, solemnly, and in the presence of God, <hi>Swear to endeavour the Reformation of Religion, according to the Word of God, and the Example of the best Reformed Churches; the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of Prelacie, and Superstition, or the Government of the Church by Arch-Bishops, Bishops, their Chancellors and Comissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp;c.</hi> and not only so, but shall importunely press the said <hi>Oath</hi> upon others; and continue in the zealous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting thereof for near twenty years together; and yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, conform to, and live in the practise of what he had thus <hi>solemnly Sworn</hi> to <hi>extirpate,</hi> he doth in effect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himself to be a <hi>False Prophet,</hi> and one who is either weake in judgment, and not able to distinguish between good
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108481:7"/>and evil: or else, which is worse, of a debauched Conscience, sining against his own light, yea against his <hi>solemn Oath:</hi> either of which render him most unworthy to be called a <hi>Minister of Christ,</hi> and must needs make it a very dangerous, or ensna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thing, for such as fear God in truth, to attend upon his preaching. For if Episcopal ordination of Ministers make it unlawful for <hi>Christians</hi> to sit under their Ministry, as is easie to demonstrate beyond contradiction: How much more unlawful is it to attend upon the Ministry of such an <hi>Episcopal Conformist,</hi> who hath laid the foundation of his Conformity, in the ruins of his own Conscience, by breaking so solemn an Oath?—But Sir, Will you be pleased to take a view of some few of your own lines, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preached, and afterwards print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the veiw of the World, pressing the Country to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in their choice of a Parliament man: thus you argue
<note n="†" place="bottom">Your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>market, Aug.</hi> 20th. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>56. printed and sold at the Bible in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> pag. 26, 27.</note>: <hi>Consider the Solemn Obligation that lies upon us, by a National Covenant, (famous through the Christian world, and we in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous for the breach of it) to promote and procure with our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most endeavours the Reformation of the Land. God hath, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, most of your hands to shew for this, and darest thou who hast bound thy self in such a Covenant, give thy voice for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy man to sit in Parliament, whom thy conscience, (if thou wouldst have patience to hear it) will tell thee, he will never be the man that will help on that work with any Vote of his, yea that is an enemy to it, and fears it more than desires it? if thou hast got the Mastery of thy Conscience so far as to do this bold a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, let me tell thee what thou dost; thou comest this day to declare in the face of all the Country, yea, before God, Men and Angels, that thou art a FORSWORN VVRETCH; and if thou gettest this brand upon thy forehead once, go where thou wilt, thou draggest a chain after thee, that will bind thee over to the fearful expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's Wrath; that (come it sooner or later) will take hold on thee. And now tell me, hadst thou not better have been asleep in thy bed, yea, sick in thy bed, yea, dead in thy grave, than to have come hither to do so unhappy a dayes work? O think when thou goest this day to give thy Suffrage for any, that thou didst see the Covenant with thy hand at it, spread before thee, &amp;c.</hi> This and more to the same effect in the foresaid Sermon.—Upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108481:8"/>which, Sir, give me leave to reason a little with you; Did the simple <hi>breach</hi> of the Covenant render men <hi>infamous?</hi> What then shall the <hi>renunciation</hi> or <hi>abjuration</hi> of it do? If a man must <hi>master his conscience</hi> before he could give his <hi>vote</hi> for a Parliament man, that would not help forward the work of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> to what degree must that Conscience be <hi>sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> that can <hi>renounce</hi> or <hi>abjure</hi> it? If he that should only give his Suffrage in this case, declared in the <hi>face of all the Country, yea before God, Men and Angels,</hi> that he was a <hi>FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SWORN VVRETCH;</hi> How many degrees more vile than a <hi>forsworn wretch</hi> is he that shall appear in the Pulpit to break this Oath, and shall under his hand renounce it? If the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>draggs a Chain after him, that will bind him over to the fearful expectation of God's wrath;</hi> how much <hi>sorer punishment,</hi> and dreadful indignation shall he be thought worthy of, that shall accept authority to preach from those, whose <hi>extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiod</hi> he swore to endeavour? If it were better that a man <hi>had been dead in his grave,</hi> than give his vote as aforesaid; were it not much better that the <hi>Abjuror</hi> or <hi>Renouncer</hi> had been thrown into the Sea, with a Milstone about his neck, before ever he had submitted to <hi>Episcopal conformity,</hi> or subscribed the <hi>Renunciation?</hi> — But, Sir, can you <hi>mock God,</hi> and <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble with men,</hi> and think to go unpunished? <hi>Be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9.</note>. It is the <hi>Fool</hi> that <hi>makes a mock at sin</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.9.</note>. What then must he be that makes a mock of God and Godliness? Or are not you partaker in a high degree, and more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manner in the wickedness of this iniquity? Preach and unpreach: Build up, and pluck down: Reform Superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Worship, and conform to Superstitions Worship: Swear, and forswear: <hi>solemnly Covenant,</hi> and <hi>with hands lifted up to the most high God, swear,</hi> that you will <hi>sincerely, really, and constantly endeavour a Reformation according to God's Word;</hi> and the <hi>extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, and Superstition, &amp;c.</hi> and then abjure, or renounce this Covenant, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently this Reformation: which to do, what is it less than to renounce or forswear all obedience to God's Law? Oh desperate Atheism! Oh abominable Prophaness! <hi>HEAR, O HEAVENS!</hi> and <hi>give car O Earth;</hi> and let all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108481:8"/>of the world be astonished: Was there ever such gross impiety perpetrated under the vizour of Godliness? May we not (with some alteration) allude to that of the Wiseman, and say, <hi>Many</hi> sons of the Church (so called) have done wickedly, but those of this age have <hi>surmounted them all</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.29.</note>. Was there ever any day wherein it might be more truly said (with the Prophet <hi>Hosea,</hi> ch. 9.7.) <hi>The Prophet is a fool, the Spiritual man is mad, for the multitude of thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, &amp;c?</hi> And again, <hi>the Lord said, The Prophets prophesie lies in my Name,</hi> I <hi>sent them not, neither have I commanded them, neither spake unto them: They prophesie unto you a false Vision and Divination, and a thing of nought, and the deceit of their heart</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.14.</note>. And thus saith the Lord, <hi>The Priests teach for hire, and the Prophets divine for money: yet will they lean upon the Lord, and say, Is not the Lord among us</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 3.11.</note>? But <hi>Wo unto the Pastors that destroy and scatter the Sheep of my Pasture, saith the Lord</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.1.</note>. And <hi>Wo unto the foolish Prophets, that follow their own spirit, and have seen nothing. O Israel, thy Prophets are like Foxes in the desarts.— They have seen vanity, and lying divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, saying, The Lord saith; and the Lord hath not sent them: and they have made others to hope, that they would confirm the word. Therefore thus saith the Lord God, Behold, I am against you, and mine hand shall be upon the Prophets that see vanity, and that divine lies: they shall not be in the Assembly of my People, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.3, 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Christ</hi> sometimes wept over <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> so may we not weep over the Inhabitants of <hi>Lavenham,</hi> together with all other places, who are led (by such <hi>blind,</hi> shall I say?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 3.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.16. <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.5.</note> nay but) by such <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>hypocritical</hi> Guides? Justly may we take up the complaint of the Prophet, <hi>O my People, they which lead thee cause thee to err, and destroy the way of thy paths.</hi> Thy Teacher (O <hi>Lavenham</hi>) doth <hi>cause thee to err, and destroy the way of thy paths;</hi> by tempting thee (if not in words, yet by actions and practices, which have the louder voice) to <hi>despise the Covenant of thy God,</hi> in building up those things, the extirpation whereof he solemnly swore to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. And now what remains? But (to allude to that of the Prophet, <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.10.) <hi>Arise ye and depart, for this is not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108481:9"/>your rest: because it is polluted, it shall destroy you even with a sore destruction.</hi> Let all that fear God forsake the tents of these men; and say every one to his own soul; <hi>Oh my soul, come not thou into their secret: unto their assembly, mine honour, be not thou united</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 49.6.</note>. But <hi>flee out of the midst of Babylon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver every man his soul: be not cut off in her iniquity</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.6.</note>. Take the counsel of God <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. and obey the exhortation of the Apostle 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. so shall you escape the wrath to come, and obtain a Crown of glory, <hi>When the times of refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing shall come from the presence of the LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>VALE.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>August</hi> 5. 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Substance of a second Letter, which (with some small enlargement) was sent to Mr. <hi>WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM GURNAL</hi> sometime after the former.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is like those few lines I lately sent you, will occasion a double consultation of thoughts within you; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. From whom they should come; and why he concealeth his Name? 2. What reasons should move him to such an undertaking?</p>
            <p>To the former, If you desire to know him, this is his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter: He is one that feareth God; and desireth to bear a testimony for him: one that dares say, <hi>It is right to obey God rather than man.</hi> And if he be enquired of concerning the <hi>Priests,</hi> he saith, <hi>Verily let God be true, though every man be found a lier;</hi> who hath said, <hi>the Priests have polluted the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary; they have done violence to the Law.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.4.</note> — <hi>As troopes of robbers waite for a man, so the company of Priests murder in the way by consent: For they commit lewdness.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hos.</hi> 6.9</note>— <hi>My Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are destroyed for lack of knowledge: Because thou hast reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed knowledge, I also will reject thee, that thou shalt be no Priest to me: seeing that thou hast forgotten the Law of thy God</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Hos.</hi> 4.6</note>— <hi>And now O ye Priests, this commandment is for you. If ye will
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108481:9"/>not hear, and if ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory unto my Name, saith the Lord of Hosts, I will even send a curse upon you, and will curse your Blessings.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.1, 2.</note>— Yea once more, if you would know him, he is one that dares not do <hi>this bold act,</hi> to <hi>declare in the face of all the Country yea before God, men, and Angels, that he is a FORSWORN Wretch,</hi> by renouncing the Covenant of his God.</p>
            <p>But for the reason why he hath thought meet at present, to conceal his Name; He needs no other Apologie, then this, That you your self cannot be so ignorant, or weak, as not to know that these are times wherein <hi>Truth faileth, and he that departeth from evil maketh himself a prey</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 59.15.</note>. How much more are they that reprove the wickedness of the Priests, like to expose themselves to the rage and malice of their ungodly Persecutors? And it seems inconsistant with wisdome and prudence for a man to lay himself open to the cruelty of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable men, when he may innocently avoid it.</p>
            <p>For the latter of the two things above mentioned, there were these three or four reasons or considerations, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with me to write the said Letter unto you. <hi>Viz.</hi> 1. The honour of God, whose Name you had greatly prophaned; and whose Glory you had trampled under foot: For what greater affront, or indignity could you offer unto God, then not onely to despise his commands, but renounce Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to his Word, and bow down before his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries? 2. The interest of <hi>Christ,</hi> and his Gospel, which were like to suffer very much by your sinful Apostacie and backsliding: If ever there was a <hi>man born to do Religion a mischief</hi> (as you use the expression borrowed from another) are not you the man? <hi>who by professing high, and living low, in sordid practises, have given Religion such a wound in its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, as is not like to be cured while you are above ground</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">See your Book, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Christian in compleat Armor,</hi> the third part. Epistle to the <hi>Reader,</hi> pag. 2.</note> Was not your pen over-ruled in that expression, as it were prophetically to set forth your own future character? or to draw the lineament of your own face? 3. The Spiritual good and preservation of the souls of men, especially such as were in most eminent danger of being ensnared through your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108481:10"/>evil example, was another cause moving me to write the said lines unto you: Your sinful example may occasion the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of many Souls; When the <hi>Priests reject the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of the Lord, <hi>the People perish.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Hos.</hi> 4.6.</note>
               <hi>The Leaders of this People cause them to erre;</hi> saith the Text; and what follows? <hi>they that are led of them are destroyed:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 9.16.</note> and no marvel though they that are <hi>led</hi> fall into the ditch, when he that <hi>leadeth</hi> them is <hi>Blind.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Matth</hi> 15.14.</note> 4. And lastly, Your own restoration and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very (if not too late) <hi>from the snare of the Devil,</hi> whom you have suffered to take you captive, as his will and pleasure was; this was another motive enducing me to the same un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking. O how would it rejoyce, not my heart onely, but the minds of all your Christian Friends and acquaintance that fear God in truth, to see you reclaimed from the evil of your way, and brought back again from <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Zion;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from your late extravagancies, to walk in the way of Godliness, from which you have so lately <hi>erred and strayed like a lost Sheep.</hi> And the Lord grant that you may never get <hi>the mastery of</hi> your own <hi>Conscience</hi> so far <hi>as to do</hi> (or rather persist in) that <hi>bold act,</hi> which your self prophesied long agoe would <hi>dragg a chain after it that will bind over to the fearful expectation of Gods wrath, that (come it sooner or later) will take hold on</hi> all impenitent Backsliders, and Hypocrites in heart. They <hi>shall be filled with</hi> their <hi>own wayes.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Pro v.</hi> 14.14.</note> And the <hi>Soul</hi> of God <hi>shall have no pleasure in them.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38.</note> But for a close I recommend two passages of Scripture more to your serious consideration. <hi>And now what hast thou to do in the way of Egypt, to drink the waters of Sihor? Or what hast thou to do in the way of Assyria, to drink the waters of the River? Thine own wickedness shall correct thee, and thy Back slidings shall reprove thee: know there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and see, that it is an evil thing and bitter, that thou hast for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken the Lord thy God, and that my fear is not in thee, saith the Lord God of Hosts.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.18, 19.</note>— <hi>The Priests lips should keep knowledge, and they should seek the Law at his mouth:— But ye are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of the way: ye have caused many to stumble at the Law: ye have corrupted the COVENANT of LEVI, saith the Lord of Hosts. Therefore have I also made you CONTEMP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIBLE and BASE before all the People.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7, 8, 9.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:108481:10"/>
            <p> Sir, I shall not burden you any further at present, save only to make this one request unto you, <hi>i. e. Remember from whence you are fallen, and Repent, and do your first works,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5.</note> lest the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> come forth against you to <hi>avenge the quarel of his Covenant.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.25.</note> Sir, <hi>knowing</hi> (in part) <hi>the terror of the Lord,</hi> give me leave to <hi>perswade</hi> you
<note n="†" place="bottom">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.</note>. In the fear of God I entreat you; and in tenderness of spirit beseech you, <hi>to search and try your wayes, and turn again to the Lord</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40.</note>. Carefully peruse, and conscientiously weigh the import of what hath been represented unto you in these Papers, and take it as an <hi>Item</hi> from God to work your repentance, and restoration: and as you tender the glory of God: the honour of Jesus Christ: the joy and consolation of the Saints: and the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Salvation of your own Soul: Yea, as you dread the fiery indignation, and fierce wrath of the Lord almighty, take heed of despising or neglecting this Sober and Christian Counsel, thus providentially administred unto you. But say with repenting Ephraim, <hi>What have I to do any more with Idols?</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hos.</hi> 14.8.</note> with <hi>Common Prayer?</hi> with <hi>Superstitious inventions?</hi> Cast them all from you as polluted; and <hi>trust in the Lord for ever; for in the Lord Jehovah is everlasting strength</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 26.4.</note>. Sir, in hope of this happy and desirable effect, I shall wait a little season, in expectation of, and diligently observing, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn you will please to make hereunto.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>VALE.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>August</hi> 27. 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>An APPENDIX.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou hast in these foregoing Letters some account how zealous Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> was for that <hi>Covenant</hi> which he hath now <hi>Renounced:</hi> Solemnly, and in the Name of God charging others to observe it; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting to their Consideration a <hi>Chain</hi> that should hold them, if the <hi>Covenant</hi> would not: wherefore I cannot see how he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108481:11"/>will escape the the <hi>righteous Judgment of God</hi> that doth <hi>the same things</hi> himself for which he <hi>judgeth another:</hi> Whether the Covenant was condemned, and the renunciation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of enjoyned right or wrong, just or unjust in the opinion of other men, is not much to him in this case, because he ought to have kept his Conscience undefiled, whatever other men did: if he believed it to be his duty to <hi>observe a day,</hi> he ought to have <hi>observed</hi> it, though another <hi>esteemed every day alike:</hi> But I perceive there are many whose zeal did not <hi>BLAZE</hi> it self as his seemed to do, that are more affraid to break an Oath then he is; and who very much question, whether the <hi>Parliament</hi> did so well consider things as they should have done, when they condemned the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> because God hath given us in the Scriptures the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of his Vengeance for the breach of two Covenants: one of which was obtained by the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> through false and subtil deceiveableness
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Josh.</hi> 9 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </note>; and entered into by <hi>Joshua,</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Israel</hi> contrary to that express Command of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.32, 33. (as Mr. <hi>George Withers,</hi> in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrance to this present Parliament well observeth) and when <hi>Saul</hi> violated it, he did it in his <hi>zeal to the children of Israel and Judah,</hi> 2 Sam. 21.2. but for all this, the blood of <hi>Saul</hi>'s house must go to appease the wrath of God for it: as appears in the forementioned chapter. The other was an Oath exacted from the King of <hi>Judah</hi> (when he was made King) by the potency of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who had him then in his hand; the breach whereof greatly provoked the wrath of God against him: as is evident, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.16.</p>
            <p>But <hi>(Reader)</hi> I shall leave this, and tell thee, that the foregoing Papers (having lain dormant a considerable space of time) are now crept out into the world, and become ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to thy view, with the addition of this <hi>Appendix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet lest the publication hereof should offend any man, I shall first give answer to an Exception that possibly may be raised by some against the printing of them: and touch a little upon that Text by which Mr. <hi>Grey</hi> seemed to plead the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108481:11"/>justification of his Conformity: And then (by occasion hereof) give thee a brief observation or two concerning the <hi>Church of England</hi> in general, and so conclude.</p>
            <p>For the first of these; Peradventure some may be ready to say, That is not well done of any man to uncover the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness of a Brother, or to lay open the infirmities of others; but if Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> had been <hi>overtaken in a fault</hi> he should have been <hi>restored in the spirit of meekness,</hi> according to the Rule of the Apostle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.</p>
            <p>For answer hereunto, first, by way of Concession; It is very true, that it becomes not a Christian Spirit to publish or divulge the <hi>infirmities of Brethren;</hi> but on the contrary to <hi>Cover the Shame of their nakedness,</hi> and endeavour their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation when <hi>overtaken in a fault:</hi> Therefore had Mr. <hi>Gur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> onely slipt or been <hi>overtaken,</hi> or surprized by an infirmity onely, I, for my part, should have been an <hi>Antagonist</hi> unto him that should have sought to spread his nakedness in that kind before the world.</p>
            <p>But,</p>
            <p>Secondly by way of exception, I answer, That this is not the case before us; first, because the Crimes that Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> stands guilty of, are not infirmities onely, but of a far deeper dye then so: for sins of infirmity only, are such miscarriages which men slip into at unawares, and out of which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to recover themselves as soon as they can. But Mr. <hi>Gurnal's</hi> Crime being notoriously wicked and ungodly, (as appears by the foregoing Letters) alters the nature of the case.</p>
            <p>Again secondly, That it is not only warrantable, but ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to God and the world, to discover the folly and madness of such, who under colour and pretence of Religion, yeild up themselves to sin and wickedness, offering violence to their own consciences, resisting the truth of the Worship and Service of God, by introducing empty shadows and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblances in the place and stead thereof, is evident beyond
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108481:12"/>contradiction, from that of the Apostle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8, 9. of which you may take farther observation at your leasure.</p>
            <p>Yet further in the third place, When the sinful miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of any men, shall have a proper tendancy in them (whilst concealed) to provoke others to, and encourage them in the same wayes of sin and unworthiness; in this case it becomes a duty upon men truly Conscientious, to endeavour their discovery; and consequently the preservation of others from being led to destruction by them. Thus the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> to keep the <hi>Galatians</hi> from being turned out of the right way of the Gospel, relateth to them the miscarriage of <hi>Peter;</hi> who though he was a great Apostle, yet in this case he spared him not, neither to his own face, nor to others; as you may see <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.14. And the like doth he do concerning the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> Tit. 1.11, 12, 13. see also to this effect 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. ver. 1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c. with many more places of like import: Now this is the case before us; Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi>'s Sin was like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger many souls; and the manifestation of his folly, is a proper means to stop the progress thereof.</p>
            <p>But once more in the fourth place; To speak properly, neither the designe, nor yet the import of these Letters, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reasonably be said, to be for the spreading or divulging of Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi>'s Sin; but they are rather an open rebuke for his Sin: The reason is plain, Because his Sin it self, is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by himself, his daily practice sounding forth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thereof, as with a Trumpet from the house top; and if every man should be silent, yet his Surplice and Common-Prayer-book-devotion, in conjunction with his Sermons up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Curse ye Meroz:</hi> and his Sermon, at <hi>Stow-market</hi> with many Engagements besides, would speak with a loud voice. Yea, the <hi>stones</hi> that he hath laid in the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> building will speak in this case. Therefore these Letters cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be saide to make his Sin publick; or to <hi>uncover his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness</hi> in the sence of the objection. But the said Letters are indeed a rebuke for his sin: and being published, they are an <hi>open rebuke.</hi> Yet herein also it is to be considered, first, That they were written and sent him in a private way, not without some hope, or expectation (as appears in them, &amp; in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108481:12"/>the Epistle) that he would have taken the <hi>secret</hi> reproof as a means to work his repentance and reformation: the Author in this expectation waites many months, but finding no fruit to arise from this his labour, but Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi> rather grows worse and worse, he first exposed them to the view of some friends more privately: and at length they become publick. By this (Reader) thou maiest perceive that if <hi>private</hi> addres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses would have done the work, this <hi>publick</hi> shame had not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen him. Now it is a manifest case, that God himself ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects that such as know and fear him, should reprove the sins of others; see for this <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. Yea, and as the case may be, <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>open rebukes,</hi> will become the duty of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.20. <hi>Them that sin, rebuke BEFORE ALL, that others also may fear.</hi> So that by this time (Christian Reader) I hope there is no <hi>rock of offence,</hi> or <hi>stumbling-stone</hi> left in the way, by reason or occasion of these Papers, or the Printing of them.</p>
            <p>As for that Scripture from which (it seems) Mr. <hi>Grey</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to plead the justification of his Conformity, (or rather Deformity) <hi>viz.</hi> Because we ought to be <hi>subject to higher powers,</hi> Rom. 13.1. It is so strange a deduction, that I much wonder how his Conscience could suffer him to bring it for such a purpose: For evident it is, that it will do him no service at all in this kind, unless he suppose, and take for granted, 1. That by <hi>Higher Powers</hi> in this Text, is meant, not only all just, and righteous Authorities amongst men, acting regularly, according to that trust which is committed to them by God: but also all, and every the Magistrates and Rulers in the world, how wicked and unworthy soever they are, or how irregularly and unwarrantably soever they act. And 2dly. That whatsoever any of the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> in this sense, shall at any time command or enjoyn those that are under them to do, be it never so sinful and ungodly, will nevertheless become their duty to do accordingly. By the help of these <hi>Premises,</hi> (I confess) <hi>Mr. Grey</hi> may easily prove his <hi>Conclusion</hi> from the forenamed Text; but I know no other <hi>medium</hi> (at least, none without these) that will do him any service in this kind. And certainly had not the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108481:13"/>
               <hi>god of this world blinded his eyes,</hi> from beholding the plain and visible discoveries of the mind of God in the Scriptures, he could never have avoided the sight of a <hi>Non-sequitur</hi> in his own Argument, for it is manifest that <hi>Paul</hi> himself (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with other Apostles and faithful Servants of God, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears both in the Old and New Testament) did from time to time suffer very cruel handling from such <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> for refusing to be subject unto them in such a sense. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly some strong <hi>Fascination</hi> had laid hold of his intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual faculty, when he entred upon so sensless a work.</p>
            <p>But if these men, (together with that great fraternity of Brethren in the same iniquity with them) to keep themselves alive in honour and repute amongst sober and good men, shall say and plead, that they have now enquired more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly into the will and mind of God than formerly they had done, and that he hath so far blessed their labour and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence herein, as to reveal unto them their former errour, and enlighten them with the knowledge of the Truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the unlawfulness of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wayes, and so brought them to repentance. I answer,</p>
            <p>That this Plea is (in the Scripture-phrase) but to <hi>adde drunkenness unto thirst</hi> and to make the sin of their act in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> and <hi>renouncing,</hi> unmeasurably sinful, may evidently appear, by considering,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is a thing not to be supposed, being almost (if not altogether) incredible, that those who had been such zealous promoters and prosecuters of it, for so long a time, should (at least so many of them together) be truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the evil of such their way and course, just at that moment of time when an Act against it should take force, and not before: Nay, that they should be so fully resolved to stand by it, one Lords-day, as <hi>Mr. Grey</hi> seemed to be; and yet the very next be able to plead the justification of the contrary. There seems more reason to judge <hi>Dr. Lee</hi> a true Penitent, because he was somewhat more deliberate; and yet I believe there is scarce one sober man to be found, who dares presume so much as to think there was one dram of true Repentance in him; but (as far as my observation reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108481:13"/>all men take him for a monster of dissimulation, still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining the same man he was before (and yet is a <hi>Changling</hi> too) meerly for wordly advantage. But</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is little less than notorious Blasphemy to ascribe the manifestly frivolous and false imaginations of a mans own heart, unto God, or to his blessing, or to the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or inspiration of his Spirit. What is this but to bear the world in hand that there is an affinity between God and the Devil; and that the distance between them, is not so great, as is commonly believed? Or can such a plea as that in the objection be any other than a frivolous conceit, or vain pretence, issuing out of the deceitful hearts of men themselves; and not from God? For how can it enter into the thoughts of any sober and considerate Christian to believe that such men who have continued many years in the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous promoting of such a way and Covenant, and (whilest the Sun of wordly countenance shined upon it) bid defiance to all Arguments that rose up against it; should in a moment and as were in the twinkling of an eye (when that Sun set) be able clearly to discern the invalidity of all those Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by which themselves and others were wont to defend it, and to obtain so thorough and satisfying a conviction, as is absolutely necessary to warrant a renunciation? He that will go about to demolish a building which himself hath been many years laying a strong foundation for, and erecting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, must (at least) take time and leasure to do it, otherwise it may tumble upon his head and crush him to peices. And more especially, such a sudden and unexpected conversion, is not like to be wrought or produced by the warm influences of wordly advantage and promotion, or where the mountain of earthly glory, seems to be the most potent and prevailing motive therein: The conversion that is effected by this means, is more like to be the <hi>off-spring of the god of this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.9.</note> then of him whose Name is <hi>Jealous.</hi> Therefore</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whereas this plea pretends that they enquired of God, about the lawfulness or unlawfulness, of their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Oath, and that in <hi>renouncing</hi> it, they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed themselves to his Answer given in unto them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108481:14"/>it; I know not where, nor of whom, to borrow any such <hi>Charity,</hi> whereby I may be enabled to believe that they consulted any other Oracle about their renouncing, than that which <hi>Demas</hi> consulted when he forsook <hi>Paul,</hi> and other good <hi>Christians,</hi> and <hi>imbraced this present world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, (and lastly) It is most unworthy a Minister of such a Gospel, which is not <hi>Yea and Nay,</hi> but <hi>Yea and Amen,</hi> in all the Promises and Sayings of it; to engage himself, both unto God and men, by a most Solemn Covenant and Oath, for the performance of such things, of the lawfulness whereof he was not groundedly, throughly, and fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded and assured, at the time of such his engagement, so that he might have no occasion to be seen playing fast and loose with Oaths. <hi>Quod-libetical</hi> actions, and matters of <hi>doubtful disputation,</hi> are ill-conditioned matter for Oaths. <hi>It is a snare to the man who devoureth that which is holy, and</hi> AF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER VOWS TO MAKE ENQUIRY, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.25. Espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially a loose and slight-built Judgment touching the things we speak of, is most insufferable in such a Minister, who was not only free, and forward, even to observation, to swear the said Covenant himself, but was an <hi>Arch Stickler</hi> also, both by Preaching and Printing, to engage others in the same Oath and Covenant with him. Such a Minister or Teacher that shall quit himself at such a desparate rate of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and folly (if not of Atheisme and prophaneness) as this, hereby renders himself notoriously irregular for so sacred a work, and becomes the man to whom God speaketh thus: <hi>What hast thou to do to take my Covenant in thy mouth, seeing thou hatest instruction, and hast cast my words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee?</hi> Psal. 50.16, 17. And he may demand of every Christian likewise: What hast thou to do to hear my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant preached, or declared, by the polluted lips of such a <hi>Renegado</hi> from his holy Profession? So that this plea of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, however it may seem to salve their credits, it is like to prove to the greater damage of their Consciences. But I proceed,</p>
            <p>And shall here give thee (Christian Reader) some obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations briefly concerning the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108481:14"/>order thereunto, I shall acquaint thee that not long since I had the view of a Manuscript in verse, containing the sad la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the <hi>Lay-man,</hi> who (it seems) was not thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful at all of any inconveniency that would follow upon the removal of <hi>Nonconformists</hi> and <hi>Non-renouncers</hi> on <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi>-day, <hi>anno</hi> 1662. (by that legal mortality; which (as the swelling Sea when it breaketh over those Banks which God hath set for <hi>Bars and doors</hi> unto it, and said, <hi>Hitherto shalt thou come but NO FURTHER,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 38.11.</note> doth much endamage the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try over which it getteth power; So this) did sweep away many precious, sober, and painful Ministers of the Gospel) but (as he there expresseth it in the name of the Country in general) was big with expectation,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.</note> that as when <hi>Elijah</hi> was taken away, a double portion of his spirit rested on <hi>Elisha,</hi> So now should there be a <hi>double portion</hi> of those mens spirits that were removed, found in them that succeeded, and in this hope went to enjoy the blessing of it. But alas! when he came, he found <hi>Elijah</hi>'s <hi>Mantle</hi> only stuft with straw; and in the Bed where holy <hi>David</hi> used to be, was nothing but a <hi>lifeless Image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he was thus bemoaning his own, and his fellow Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try mens loss, he was over-heard and sharply rebuked by a proud <hi>Prelate,</hi> who told him, that he much undervallued those that were now appointed for their Teachers: Which the plain-hearted <hi>Layman</hi> thought was so far from truth, and the contrary so manifest, that he proceeds on still, and tels the <hi>Prelate</hi> that the best of them, were those that either through ignorance, or against the light of their own Consciences had conformed, either for fear, or filthy lucre: and that if these were excepted, the rest were <hi>Flagella proximorum,</hi> so many scourges unto their neighbours, and plagues to those Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes to which they respectively relate. Take it in his own words,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Take out those few, and every one oth' rest,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Call them not Parish Priests, but Parish <hi>Pests.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And a little after, taking notice of their Schollarship, he saith, That they have made so little proficiency in Christian learning, that they can scarce <hi>decline Bacchus and Venus;</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:108481:15"/>if so, then that Lesson which the Apostle hath set for all Christians, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.22. in these words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, will be to hard for these Teachers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to learn.</p>
            <p>Now if those that are <hi>natural sons</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> have learned so little <hi>Christianity,</hi> and those who are <hi>sons by law,</hi> are the best; (as this <hi>Lay-man</hi> affirmeth (and that his testimony herein is true, is the opinion of all in the Nation, (as far as I can perceive) that have their sences exercised (though but a little) to discern good and evil.) Then may we conclude that these, and such like, are the men that the Apostle speaks of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>Who resist the Truth as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses;</hi> namely, by doing something like to Ministers of Christ, as <hi>Jannes and Jambres</hi> did some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like to those miracles which <hi>Moses</hi> wrought: but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding this, <hi>their folly</hi> shall be <hi>made manifest to all men, as theirs also was:</hi> And if <hi>Christians</hi> will follow the Apostles direction, ver. 5. to <hi>turn away from them,</hi> they may hinder them from <hi>proceeding any further:</hi> and (methinks) those who stand disposed in heart and soul, to hearken to the counsel of God, should not dare to reject this injunction of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle: Neither can they long continue to shroud them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves under the wings of such unnatural Brooders, unless they quite degenerate from those rational principles, which as they are men, God hath planted in them; but will seek for the waters of life in purer streams: like as young Ducks which though they have been hatched under a Hen, yet will not continue with her upon the dunghil, if they can but find the refreshing water-brooks.</p>
            <p>And if those who are <hi>sons by Law,</hi> yeild to the Church of <hi>England</hi> her greatest glory, then hath she none that will much commend her; for these <hi>coming by the By</hi> (as we use to say) loudly proclaim her unto the world for a <hi>Whorish Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:</hi> And how she will escape the Blot of being reputed an <hi>Adulteress,</hi> that can so freely receive (if not impudently invite) unto her other <hi>lovers</hi> besides Christ, and have Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by them (as she hath had by Kings and Rulers) I do not well understand: and there is this circumstance that aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108481:15"/>her sin, to wit, that these whom she hath entertained, are those whom Christ had predeclared would be his <hi>enemies,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Matth</hi> 10.17, 18.</note> as by too sad experience we find to be true; For now they have entered this unclean conjunction, how do they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to destroy, and <hi>banish</hi> those who are truly begotten by the overshadowings of the Spirit of God? The only way that I know left her, to remove this <hi>ignominious</hi> brand, is, to <hi>renounce</hi> (as she hath done the Covenant) all relation to <hi>Christ</hi> as her Husband; and then, though she will not appear to be an <hi>Adulteress,</hi> yet will she plainly declare her self to be (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed she is) a <hi>strange Woman,</hi> whom the Wiseman deciphers, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5. and perswadeth us by many weighty reasons, to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move far from her, and not come near the door of her house,</hi> and chap. 7. declareth how the <hi>Simple man void of understanding,</hi> was allured and drawn in by her, <hi>as an Ox to the slaughter,</hi> or <hi>as a fool to the correction of the stocks: till a dart strike through his liver.</hi> I could wish that <hi>Christians</hi> would consider these places, and apply them to spiritual cases; for spiritual whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is much more destructive than that which is corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally such.</p>
            <p>One of those considerations by which (amongst many other weighty motives) the Wiseman endeavours to disswade men from coming near the door of this <hi>strange womans</hi> house, is this, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>her steps take hold on Hell,</hi> chap. 5.5. <hi>i.e.</hi> by an <hi>hypallage,</hi> Hell taketh hold on her steps; meaning that her wayes are so near the brink of Hell, that no man can go in unto her, without eminent danger of falling irrecoverably into that lake of perdition. Now that the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> herein beareth this her <hi>lewd Sister</hi> company, is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evident to such of the Servants of God, whose sences are competently exercised in <hi>discerning between things that differ;</hi> as might easily be made appear by many demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive considerations, which my intended brevity permits me not at present to insist upon; Only besides what hath been already hinted to this purpose, I here add, That the <hi>Church of England</hi> giveth heed to <hi>doctrines of Devils:</hi> Now whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>doth</hi> so, approacheth <hi>very near the mouth of Hell,</hi> and therefore it may well be said, that their <hi>steps take hold on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108481:16"/>it:</hi> What those doctrines are, the Apostle giveth us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. <hi>forbiding to marry, and commanding to abstain from meats:</hi> both which are not only practised by this Church, but are things wherein she boasteth her self, and whereof she maketh open and publick profession. And the reason why they are called <hi>Doctrines of Devils</hi> may be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are of their dictating, and contradictory to those Constitutions which God hath appointed, implicitly taxing these with imperfection, and their Author with want of wisdome; hereby occasioning men to turn aside from the way of the Lord, which causeth him to withdraw from them, by which means the Devil getteth ground, and by degrees insensibly maketh them his captives to serve him at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: Now seeing these things are so plainly laid down by the Apostle for <hi>Doctrines of Devils,</hi> I cannot but think that this Church is judicially led unto these practices, that we may know she is <hi>departed from the Faith, and avoid her.</hi> The further evincing the truth of this Argument, as it resates to the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and the dissipating of all those colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable pretences by which some men (devoted to the love of this Strange Woman) seek to defend her, as one not at all concerned in the Scripture, lately quoted, is a work so easie and facile, that I judge it needless here any further to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate it: Nor yet to detain my Reader much longer in this matter, otherwise it were a near-hand consideration to shew that (together with others of the like demerit) the Apostle pointeth out this <hi>Church of England</hi> (in the Scripture men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) by bringing her practice to the touchstone of the 2d <hi>vers. Speaking lies in hypocrisie, having their Consciences seared with a hot iron.</hi> For what is it to <hi>speak lies in hypocrisie,</hi> but to pretend one thing in a fair and plausible manner, and to intend another? and that this is a practice unto which she is accustomed, is too too manifest to all men: For how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently doth she hypocritically pretend <hi>the honour of God, and good of Saints;</hi> when her chiefest aim is to further some un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and carnal interest or other? for that her end is not the honour of God, is manifest from hence; because she doth not only bear with patience, but freely imbrace, and lovingly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108481:16"/>receive, such into her bosome-communion, who are Open Transgressors of the Law of God, and devote themselves to the Prophanation of his Name and Glory in the world: but such as are truly conscientious, and fear God, she can take no delight in; which could not be if the honour of God was the thing she aimed at.</p>
            <p>Again, If her <hi>Conscience were not seared with an hot Iron,</hi> she could never proceed with so little regret, to trample up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all those Scriptures which rise up in sull opposition to most of her beloved wayes: nor could she rest so supinely and quietly, as she seemeth to do, under the transaction of such things in the Nation, partly (if not wholly) for her sake, which must needs draw down the Vengeance of God upon it: of which nature is the cruel handling and banishing of persons, for no other cause but their serving of God: a thing so abominable and unchristian, that some of their own party are astonished at it, and seem to be very sensible that some sore Judgement of God is like to follow upon it; because those whom they sentence to Banishment, are <hi>sober:</hi> and themselves regardless of the Law of God, and a <hi>prophane, swearing generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But because I am upon the pin of brevity, and in regard the parity and agreement between the <hi>Church of England</hi> and this <hi>strange woman,</hi> is a thing so obvious and plain in it self, I shall insist no more upon it at present; only add, That see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is so, that this Church we speak of, is a walking-mate of that strange womans, whose <hi>steps take hold on Hell;</hi> let all that desire to escape that pit of destruction, be warned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to take the Wiseman's counsel, <hi>Remove thy way far from her, and come not near the door of her house,</hi> Prov. 5.8.</p>
            <p>But whilest we are speaking of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> it will not be amiss to enquire where we may finde her, seeing there are some men of opinion, that there is no such thing, as this Church we now speak of, in <hi>rerum natura,</hi> among things that exist; but that we are imposed upon in her name, by some other person: as the <hi>Persians</hi> were in respect of their King when <hi>Cambises</hi> died; <hi>Patizithes</hi> the Vice-Roy making his own son King in the name of <hi>Smerdis,</hi> the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108481:17"/>of <hi>Cambises,</hi> who (it seems) was slain
<note n="†" place="bottom">Heylen's <hi>little Descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the great World.</hi> pag. 638.</note>: Neither is their judgment in this case altogether without ground to support it, for (to use the terms of these sons of the Church themselves, so called) all the Laity wholly, and all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie below the dignity of their Bishops, they call <hi>[Sons of the Church,]</hi> and the Bishops they call <hi>[Fathers of the Church]</hi> So that the Church her self appears by this to be a meer <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> between the <hi>Fathers</hi> and the <hi>Sons,</hi> they devour the <hi>Mother,</hi> and leave her no being at all: and it would be well for the Nation if her Name were <hi>Null</hi> also.</p>
            <p>Though some there be that think this no inconvenience at all, but plead that the same men may be <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Sons</hi> of the Church, and yet the <hi>Church her self</hi> too; which mystery seems meer confusion; because it is impossible there should be any Body in being, the Members whereof are its own Fathers, or Sons; much less both.</p>
            <p>However, let us see what it is that themselves, and their Advocates take to be this Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of them herein, we must know, that they have a twofold acceptation of this Church, according to the nature of those things relating to her, which the occasion leadeth them to discourse of; for if they speak of the Orders or Ceremonies of the Church, they mean such things as are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned or appointed to be used in their Ecclesiastical Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies (for we never hear of any thing decreed or appointed <hi>BY the Church:</hi>) Upon such occasions as these, by the <hi>Church</hi> they understand these <hi>Ecclesiastical Assemblies.</hi> But when they speak of the benefits or profits of the Church, by <hi>Church</hi> then, they understand those only who officiate in these As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, and more especially the benefic'd Clergy, but chiefly and most principally the dignitaries, as Bishops and Deans, &amp;c. the rest being no sharers in these.</p>
            <p>This being the Church in their own sense, it is impossible they should by their Church-Laws, meddle with such as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come at their Assemblies, if they would take the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> for their example, who saith, <hi>What have I to do to judge</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> to deal with) <hi>them that are without? do not ye judge them that are within?</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12.</note> meaning them only: but these men
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108481:17"/>instead of judging those that are within, suffer them for the most part, to live in what sinful course they please, without any punishment for it; much less do they refuse to <hi>eat with such a brother that is a Fornicator, or Coveteous, or an Idolater, or a Railer, or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner,</hi> which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle chargeth the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> to do, and in them all other Churches: But they on the contrary make it their main business to judge them that are without, as if they did it on purpose to contradict the Apostle's rule: By which it is evident, that this <hi>Church of England,</hi> as in her being, so in her practice, she is an <hi>alien from God,</hi> and the Scriptures know her not: her rise and original is not from above; and her wayes and practices are governed by some other Rules, opposite to what are found in the Word of God.</p>
            <p>But it would far surpass my intention of brevity, should I take notice of all those things which make her look with a very uncomely and deformed shape and countenance; for as she is regardless of the Rule of the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> (as was just now hinted) so neither doth she make any provision that those who walk with her, may be in a capacity to put that <hi>Direction</hi> of our Saviour into practice, recorded, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17. <hi>Moreover, if thy brother shall trespass against thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him alone: if he shall hear thee, thou hast gained thy brother. But if he will not hear thee, then take with thee one or two more, that in the mouth of two or three witnesses every word may be established. And if he shall neglect to hear them, tell it unto the Church: but if he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen man and a Publican.</hi> For, first, the relation of <hi>Brethren,</hi> is lost among persons of her societies; so that a man (under her covert) knoweth not where to find this <hi>Brother,</hi> by whom he ought thus to deal; nor 2ly. doth he know where to find the Church, to whom he ought to <hi>tell the matter;</hi> none of their Congregations bearing this name.</p>
            <p>And lastly, That which our Saviour hath here appointed for the utmost punishment, will not satisfie the revengeful minds of such as comply with this Church, but by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their Mother, they proceed often times to undo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108481:18"/>their neighbours, and to drive them from their habitations: So that here is another of their misdemeanours (to say no worse) by which it appears that she is no Church of Christ's constitution, nor walketh in the order of his Gospel. I might heap up instances of this kind even unto weariness: For,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Should I run over each deformity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which on the Church of</hi> England <hi>I espy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The time would fail me, life would be too short,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hereof to give a just and full report.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore to conclude; as that Generation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in whose time our Saviour was conversant upon Earth, was so irregular that he knew not well unto whom to liken them; <hi>Luke</hi> 7.31. But saith, vers. 32. <hi>they are like unto Children sitting in the Market-place, &amp;c.</hi> even so, were he now again on the Earth I know not unto what he would liken this <hi>Church of England</hi> more fitly, than to those <hi>lifeless Organs,</hi> which themselves have set up in their <hi>Cathedrals,</hi> upon which one thus discanteth:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They make the outside of their Organs shine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As sometime did</hi> Diana's <hi>silver Shrine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But yet their breathless Wind-pipes make no noise,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till wind by humane art, doth give them voice:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men carnal form them, for mens carnal ends;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men carnal act them: Bishops them defends:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men carnal praise them, for advantage sake;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men Godly, in them, can no pleasure take:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heart, Soul, and Spirit-service must give way,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That carnal men may hear these Organs play.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Unto these may she well be likened: for, 1. The reason of her being is the same with them, <hi>viz.</hi> the carnal ends of men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is too apparent that men of carnal principles were her Formers, there is so little spirituality in her Make.</p>
            <p n="3">3. She hath no motion but what is given unto her by men; for she doth nothing as she is a Church, but hath all her orders made to her hand, without which she is able to say,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108481:18"/>or do, nothing at all: altogether unlike that Gospel Church we read of <hi>Act.</hi> 15. who of their own authority assembled, and resolved upon a matter in question, and authorized some to declare this their resolution.</p>
            <p n="4">4. She hath few (if any) that will open their mouths on her behalf, but such as hope for worldly advantage thereby; and from these she may receive some weak applause.</p>
            <p n="5">5. She is also distastful to Sober and Godly men, even as the Organs are.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To make way for this Church, men are molested and hindered in the performance of those services to God, which are spiritual, and required of them by God himself, and which their Consciences enjoyn them to perform.</p>
            <p n="7">7. She hath the same Patriots, to wit, such a sort of Bishops, which the Word of God, and the Appointments of Jesus Christ, take no knowledge of: and from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of any other, no Officer is to be received into his Church. In these seven particulars doth this <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and her <hi>Organs,</hi> very well sute and agree; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no wonder she is so greatly in love with them since they do so exactly bear her image. Therefore, <hi>Save your selves from this untoward generation</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.40.</note>. <hi>Little Children keep your selves from Idols</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.21.</note>. For the day of the Lord is drawing on apace, wherein <hi>he shall utterly abolish the Idols:</hi> And the <hi>loftiness of man shall be bowed down,</hi> and the <hi>haughtiness of men shall be made low:</hi> and <hi>the Lord alone shall be exalted in that day;</hi> for he shall <hi>arise to shake terribly the Earth:</hi> Then shall men <hi>cast their Idols of Silver, and their Idols of Gold, to the Moles and to the Bats:</hi> and <hi>go into the clefts of the Rocks, and into the tops of the ragged Rocks, for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his Majesty</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 2.</note>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 7. line 20. for <hi>inroad</hi> read <hi>inroads.</hi> p. 8. in the marg. f. <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.5. r. 5.4. p. 12. l. 1.1. <hi>down and.</hi> p. 13. l. 17. dele <hi>in.</hi> p. 14. l. 16, 17. 1. <hi>extirpation.</hi> p. 15. l. 9. r. <hi>Prophets.</hi> p. 20. l. 1. dele <hi>the.</hi> p. 21. l. 5. 1. <hi>it is not.</hi> l. <hi>ult.</hi> f. <hi>theteof</hi> 1. <hi>thereof.</hi> p. 23. l. 16. f. <hi>the way</hi> r. <hi>thy way.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>